Mohammad Tanzil Alam

• Alter Winterweg 9, 28237 Bremen, Germany +4917674560350 mohammadtanzilalam@gmail.com

ntanzil in tanzil

Data Engineer with 3+ years of experience in the healthcare and software sectors, specializing in optimization and effective communication of solutions to stakeholders. My robust problem-solving skills, enhanced by critical and analytical thinking, are key in tackling complex data challenges.

Skills

General Skills:

ETL & Data Pipelines Design & Development, Big Data Technologies, Cloud Computing, Agile Methodologies, Version control, Containerization, Data warehousing, DevOps.

Technical Skills:

Python, Spark, Apache Airflow, dbt, Java, Linux, Git (CI/CD), AWS, SQL, Kanban, MS PowerBI.

Soft Skills

Problem-Solving, Analytical, Attention to detail, Critical thinking, Technical Leadership, Communication, Data-driven.

Work Experience

Data Engineer

02/2023 - 07/2023 | Penzberg, Germany

Roche Diagnostics GmbH

- Establish a Python ETL data pipeline to manage and clean large and complex datasets to ensure data reliability and integrity for all scientific investigations.
- Leveraged text mining and Natural Language Processing (NLP) to extract key insights from unstructured data.
- Designed ML and advanced mathematical metrics techniques that improved results by 99.5%.
- Created Python library to parse data from external sources, reducing manual effort and error in the data pipeline.
- Implemented CI/CD pipeline using DevOps tools: Git, AWS and Docker, reducing deployment time by 70% by automating the process.

Apprentice Data Engineer

06/2022 - 08/2022 | Penzberg, Germany

Roche Diagnostics GmbH

- Designed an automated AWS data pipeline in digital healthcare, processing TBs of data.
- Optimized data pipelines using AWS Glue, S3 and Athena to support data analytics/curation operations.
- Implemented ETL process utilizing PySpark to transform and load data into centralized datalake.
- Optimized SQL queries in AWS Athena to support data curation.
- Participated in daily stand-up meetings and bi-weekly sprint planning sessions as part of an agile development team.

Senior Software Engineer

05/2020 – 05/2021 | Kolkata, India

Fortress6 Technologies

- Engineered a faster data retrieval system, reducing search time by 60%. Used SQL optimization strategies.
- Implemented Infrastructure as Code (IaC) tools like Terraform, and CloudFormation for provisioning AWS resources.
- Mentored a team of 5 junior developers, introducing a code review process, and improving code quality by 25%.
- Spreadheaded an automation project with Python which decreased manual process time by 70%. Used GitHub Actions for efficient Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (CI/CD).

Junior Software Engineer

06/2019 - 04/2020 | Kolkata, India

Fortress6 Technologies

- Assisted senior developers in the development and maintenance of the backend system, resulting in a positive impact on the company's performance.
- Introduced Git for version control, improving code management efficiency.
- Worked closely with cross-functional teams to deliver high-quality software on tight deadlines.

Mohammad Tanzil Alam 1/2

Education

Master of Science in Data Engineering

Jacobs University Bremen

09/2021 – 08/2023 | Bremen, Germany

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science & Engineering

Uttarakhand Technical University

08/2015 - 05/2019 | Dehradun, India

Language

Hindi/Urdu	English	German/ Deutsch
Native	Fluent	Working Proficiency

Awards/ Certifications

Recipient of a 100% scholarship for an MSc studies.

Roche Cooperative Study Program

Academic merit scholarship

Jacobs University Bremen

AWS Cloud Computing and Deployment.

WebTek Labs Pvt. Ltd.

A+ in MySQL training from Microsoft, ranking among the top 5%

Microsoft Technology Associate

Mohammad Tanzil Alam 2 / 2